Etelman Family Papers MS204
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Etelman Family Papers
1919 -- 1997
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Carl Etelman family
Etelman, Carl, 1900-1963
Etelman, Idyla, 1903-1986
MS204
4.35 Linear Feet
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into three series: Carl Etelman and Idyla Gould Etelman papers; Barbara G. Fullington papers; and Etelman family papers.
Biographical / Historical
Carl Etelman (1900-1963) was the first Tufts alum to play professional football. Carl Etelman was born on April 1, 1900 in Fairhaven, Massachusetts. After attending Fairhaven High School, he enrolled at Tufts College in 1920. While at Tufts, Etelman was a member of Phi Epsilon Pi and a letterman in football, baseball, basketball, track, and wrestling. He is perhaps best known for kicking a 48-yard field goal with a broken foot, helping Tufts defeat Massachusetts Agricultural College (later the University of Massachusetts Amherst) in the final game of the 1923 season. After receiving his Bachelor's from Tufts in 1924, Carl Etelman went on for graduate study at Boston University and Harvard University.
Following the 1923 football season, the New York Times named Carl Etelman quarterback of their All-Eastern team. He went on to play one season with the Boston Bulldogs of the American Football League and a few games with the Providence Steam Rollers of the National Football League before retiring from playing professionally.
Following his stint as a professional football player, Carl Etelman taught and coached football at Whitman High School in Whitman, Massachusetts for 18 years. Starting in 1945 and continuing until his death in 1963, he was a sales manager for Ward Machinery Co. of Brockton, Massachusetts. Carl Etelman was heavily involved in a number of civic endeavors. He was a past master of the Puritan and Ezra Lodges, chairman of the finance committee of his local Republican Party, director of several youth camps, and Chairman of the Temple Israel Hebrew School in Brockton, Massachusetts, where he helped found the Tufts South Shore Club.
Carl Etelman passed away on December 18, 1963 in Boston, Massachusetts at the age of 63.
Idyla Etelman (1903-1986) was a Jackson College alum and a recipient of the Distinguished Service Award. Idyla Etelman was born Idyla Florence Gould on February 24, 1903, in Russia. She moved to the United States at the age of 3, and thereafter grew up in Barre, Vermont. After studying at Goddard Seminary, she enrolled in Jackson College in the fall of 1921. While at Jackson, Etelman was president of the Knight House and an officer of the History Club. In her junior year, she was the Phi Beta Kappa speaker. Idyla Etelman graduated summa cum laude with a Bachelor's from Jackson College in 1925.
Following graduation from Tufts, Idyla Etelman was a teacher in Westerly, Rhode Island; Plymouth, Massachusetts; Pembroke, Massachusetts; and Marshfield, Massachusetts, where she was the head of the Marshfield High School English Department.
Idyla Etelman was awarded the Distinguished Service Award by Tufts in 1967. She was a life member of the Jackson Association of Tufts Alumnae, co-chaired every Class of 1925 reunion for fifty years, and was a charter member of the Tufts South Shore Club. In 1967, it was estimated that Idyla Etelman's efforts as a teacher and volunteer were responsible for sending more than one hundred students to Tufts.
Idyla F. Gould married Carl Etelman after meeting at Tufts and took Etelman's last name. They had one daughter, Barbara, and one son, Richard. Idyla Etelman passed away on April 7, 1986 in Wellesley, Massachusetts at the age of 83.
Barbara Fullington (1928-) is a Jackson alum and a recipient of the Distinguished Service Award.
Barbara Fullington was born Barbara G. Etelman in 1928 to Carl and Idyla Etelman. She enrolled at Jackson College in 1943 and received her Bachelor's degree in 1947. Over the course of her career, Barbara Fullington was a teacher, author, and the Director of Publicity and Exhibits for the Newton Free Library.
Barbara was a life member of the Jackson Association of Tufts Alumnae, member of the Executive Board of the Alumni Council, and co-chair of several reunions. She was awarded the Distinguished Service Award by Tufts in 1975.
Babara Etelman married a lawyer named George Michaels and had two daughters that they raised together in Newton, Massachusetts. The couple divorced after nearly thirty years of marriage. Barbara Etelman later remarried to Professor Norbert L. Fullington, with whom she stayed until his death in 2001.
Custodial History
Vertical files for Carl and Idyla Etelman originally created by the Development office have been removed from UA073 and added to this collection.
Scope and Contents
This collection is composed of photographs, publications, scrapbooks, postcards, and ephemera from the 1920s to the 1990s. The material in the collection belonged to members of the Etelman family, most notably Carl Etelman, Idyla Gould Etelman, and Barbara G. Fullington. The collection includes official Tufts photographs and publications as well as personal materials such as photographs, correspondence, and Boston-area ephemera. Also included are scrapbooks, publications, and ephemera relating to other members and acquaintances of the Etelman family.
Alumni collections; University history; Tufts University -- History; Jackson College for Women (Tufts University); Tufts University; Etelman, Richard G., 1904-1978; Gould, Benjamin D., 1904-1978
- Carl Etelman and Idyla Gould Etelman papers, 1919 -- 1975; MS204.001; 4.15 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series is composed of photographs, scrapbooks, correspondence, publications, artifacts, and ephemera owned by Carl and Idyla Etelman. The bulk of the material dates from 1920 to 1975. The material largely relates to Carl and Idyla's time at Tufts and subsequent Tufts class reunions. Also included are artifacts of their personal and professional lives. Of particular note are Carl Etelman's scrapbook relating to his football career and social life, 1919-1937, and a binder containing personal updates from members of the Class of 1925 in anticipation of their 50th reunion.
  Arrangement
  This series is not arranged.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Annual Reports of the Association of New England Football Officials, 1948 -- 1951; MS204.001.001.00001 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Carl Etelman Football Photograph, 1924; MS204.001.001.00002 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Class of 1925 Reunion Letter Draft, 1950; MS204.001.001.00003 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Class of 1925 Tufts College 50th Anniversary and Reunion, 1975; MS204.001.001.00004 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Delta Kappa Gamma, 1949 -- 1974; MS204.001.001.00005 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Ezra Lodge - Wor. Carl Etelman Honorary Life Member Card, 1953; MS204.001.001.00006 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Hockey, Varsity and Subs Photograph, 1922; MS204.001.001.00007 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
    Names of atheletes on back of photograph.
  - Idyla F. Gould Report Cards, 1922 -- 1924; MS204.001.001.00008 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Idyla Gould Poetry, 1925; MS204.001.001.00009 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - John Ciardi Bibliography and Correspondence, 1960 -- 1962; MS204.001.001.00010 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Munro Photographs of Carl Etelman and Idyla F. Gould, 1924; MS204.001.001.00011 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Official NCAA Football Handbook for Coaches and Officials, 1951; MS204.001.001.00012 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Pembroke High School and KHS Materials, 1950 -- 1967; MS204.001.001.00013 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Photographs of Student Athletes and Cheerleaders, 1923 -- 1924; MS204.001.001.00014 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
    Single page originally from scrapbook.
  - Pilgrim Chapter, no. 89 Meeting Programs, 1959 -- 1964; MS204.001.001.00015 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Postcards Addressed to Idyla, 1963 -- 1966; MS204.001.001.00016 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Puritan Lodge Meeting Programs, 1960 -- 1970; MS204.001.001.00017 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Tufts Ivy Books, 1920 -- 1922; MS204.001.001.00018 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
    Feature many handwritten notes.
  - 25th Reunion Class of 1924 Photograph, 1949-06-18; MS204.001.001.00019 (Box Small Map Case 1 Drawer 1)
    Oversize photograph.
  - Etelman, Carl A 1924 [Vertical File], 1950 -- 1963; MS204.001.001.00044 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Etelman, Idyla Gould J 1925 (Idyla F. Gould) [Vertical File], 1975; MS204.001.001.00045 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Bowser's Candies of Preference Menu, 1925; MS204.001.001.00047 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Carl Etelman Brockton Enterprise Obituary Plaque, 1963-12-19; MS204.001.002.00001 (Box MS204 Shared 2)
  - Class of 1925 25th Reunion Correspondence and Personal Information Sheets, 1950; MS204.001.002.00002 (Box MS204 Shared 2)
  - Demosthenes Nicholas Protopapas Ballcap, 1924; MS204.001.002.00003 (Box MS204 Shared 2)
  - Carl Etelman 1900-1963 Scrapbook, 1919 -- 1937; MS204.001.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook, 1925; MS204.001.004.00001 (Box 4)
    This is an unidentified scrapbook containing Tufts and non-Tufts related material from the 1920s.
  - Loose Material from Front of Scrapbook, 1925; MS204.001.004.00002 (Box 4)
    This folder is comprised of loose material that was inside the front cover of the above scrapbook (MS204.001.004.00001). It has been removed from the scrapbook to prevent any further damage.
- Barbara G. Fullington papers, 1944 -- 1997; MS204.002; 1.75 Linear Feet
  This series is composed of photographs, publications, correspondence, programs, negatives, and slides owned by Barbara G. "Bobbe" (Etelman) Fullington. The bulk of the material dates from 1944 to 1997. The material largely relates to Barbara's time at Tufts, 1943-1947, and subsequent class reunions.
  - Class of 1947 50th Reunion Photographs, 1997; MS204.002.001.00020 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Class of 1947 Tufts University in 1972: Twenty-Fifth Reunion, MS204.002.001.00021 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Concert by the Tufts College Chorus and Tufts College Orchestra, Goddard Chapel, Program, 1946; MS204.002.001.00022 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Football Program - Boston University vs. Tufts College, 1945; MS204.002.001.00023 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - The Ice-Cream Short Story, 1947; MS204.002.001.00024 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Photograph of Norma Phillips, J47, 1947; MS204.002.001.00025 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Postcards Addressed to Bobbe, 1945 -- 1946; MS204.002.001.00026 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Reunion Tufts Bobbe #1 Slides, 1962; MS204.002.001.00027 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Student Portraits - Bettie & Bobbie, 1947; MS204.002.001.00028 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Test Answers, 1947; MS204.002.001.00029 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Tufts 97 Negatives, 1997; MS204.002.001.00030 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Tufts Weekly Class of '47 Reunion Issue, 1972; MS204.002.001.00031 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Voo Doo Magazine, 1944 -- 1945; MS204.002.001.00032 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - World War II Military Publications, 1945; MS204.002.001.00048 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Boston Playbills and Programmes, 1946; MS204.002.001.00049 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Class of 1947 40th Reunion Photograph, 1987; MS204.002.002.00005 (Box MS204 Shared 2)
    Folder located on top of box.
- Etelman family papers, 1922 -- 1990; MS204.003; 1.95 Linear Feet
  This series is composed of publications, photographs, artifacts, news clippings, and a scrapbook relating to the Etelman family, their acquaintances, and Tufts. The bulk of the material dates from 1922 to 1985. Of particular note is a scrapbook highlighting aspects of daily life for Jackson and Tufts students in the 1920s compiled by Idyla's roommate Mabel Choate, various mid-20th century Tufts publications, and a Jackson College 75th anniversary plate.
  - Alumni! Get on the ball with Jumbo, 1949; MS204.003.001.00033 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Class Day Program, 1928; MS204.003.001.00034 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - I'd send my son to Tufts - John Holmes, 1933; MS204.003.001.00035 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Mayoralty Campaign Photographs, 1946; MS204.003.001.00036 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Newsclippings, 1925 -- 1958; MS204.003.001.00037 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Notes on Conrad, MS204.003.001.00038 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Richard Gould Etelman, Exeter Pean, 1947; MS204.003.001.00039 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Songs of Sigma Kappa, 1930; MS204.003.001.00040 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
    Copy owned by Virginia Call.
  - Tufts College 1859 Color Reproduction, 1970; MS204.003.001.00041 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Tufts Name Badges, 1950; MS204.003.001.00042 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Unidentified Photographs, 1928 -- 1990; MS204.003.001.00043 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Boston Globe Football Cartoons, 1938; MS204.003.001.00046 (Box MS204 Shared 1)
  - Mabel Choate Scrapbook, 1922 -- 1926; MS204.003.002.00004 (Box MS204 Shared 2)
    Scrapbook compiled by Mabel Choate, Idyla Gould's roommate.
  - Jackson College 75th Anniversary Plate and Alumni Weekend Brochure, 1985-05-16 -- 1985-05-19; MS204.003.005.00001 (Box 5)